Revinda Taylor is a voice for grounded
wisdom, scientific insight, and lived
transformation. With a degree in
microbiology, formal training in
psychotherapy and hypnotherapy, and
decades of collaboration with
best-selling author Elden Taylor,
Rainder has spent over 30 years
exploring how the mind shapes every part
of our lives. She's co-authored more
than 200 personal development programs,
but her most personal work yet is Mind
Training: The Science of
Self-Empowerment. I read it. It's great.
A book born from research, resilience,
and her own self-healing journey after
being diagnosed with rheumatoid
arthritis. This conversation goes deep
in into subconscious rewiring, optimism,
identity, and the real mechanics for
inner change. Rainder doesn't offer
cliches or hype. She offers real tools
for real transformation. Let's get into
it. Junko Club podcast. At what age do
we learn how to act better?
Junkyard Love podcast. Hey, welcome to
the podcast. Who are you and what is it
that you do? Well, hi Jacob. Thanks so
much for having me on. I am Rainda
Taylor. Um, I'm there's lots of things.
You know, when you try to say who am I,
that's a really big a really big
question. I'm fascinated with the power
of the mind. And so, that's a huge
aspect of my world is trying to find out
why we do what we do. Um, and not only
on, you know, from a theoretical
perspective, but from a very practical
perspective. I'm all about becoming the
best version of myself possible. And
they do say, you teach what it is that
you want to learn. And so, as I'm
learning more about how to become the
best version of me, then as I teach that
to other people, I get a much deeper
grounding in that. So, yeah, it's all
about be becoming the best the best
version of me. It's not about being
superwoman or being perfect in any way.
It's about removing the blockages in my
life so that I can express my authentic
self. Yeah. Wonderful. Okay. So, how did
how did you land all of that information
that you've gathered over all these
years of living your life and and
accumulating all of this wealth of
information? How did it land into the
book Mind Training?
Actually, that was a little bit
accidental. My my husband is Elden
Taylor. He is a New York Times
best-selling author. He's created the
patented inner talk subliminal
technology. So, I've spent a great deal
of time working in the background
supporting him with his work, doing lots
of the research. I do lots of the
editing. But then I came across a
scientific paper that grabbed my
interest for strange reasons. Actually,
this particular scientific study, they
were talking about a 12minute meditation
that was shown to enhance cognitive
abilities, reverse dementia, improve
health. It was having all of these very
definite positive results and that
that's fascinating. But it was the
meditation itself that grabbed my
attention and showed me that I have a
lot to contribute. I've got my own
stories, my own experiences, my own
perspective. So, this particular
meditation, you may have heard of it, is
the Sarta Nama.
I have it. It's it's a simple 12minute
meditation. Um, as I said, fabulous
fabulous results. They've done follow-up
research on it. So they've approached it
from from different perspectives and it
has been shown over and over again to
improve cognitive abilities and reverse
dementia, maybe reverse some
Alzheimer's, alleviate some of those
symptoms. But the reason Satan
ars even when you move away from your
religious upbringings, those things
still have a hold on you. So I was
bought up a sik. um I don't consider my
seek anymore consider myself to be seek
anymore because I don't follow those
rules but there are lots of the
teachings that are just ingrained within
me sat nama when I heard that it's like
that sounds so much like satnam
um and so I went digging digging around
satnam is basically the second word that
is used in the seek holy book the gurug
gransai satna mom. So I I dug around to
it and I found out that this research
was carried out by a guy who is sick. He
he started it. It's not he didn't do all
all the research. As I said, the
research is very solid. He's got lots of
um great professionals, academics, uh
professors working on it. Um so it it is
very solid but he is a seek and what I
found was some of these explanations
that were given to the background. So
what is advert what was advertised
widely was that sata nama meant um
something like birth life death rebirth
something like that and that's not what
it means but I questioned myself I'm not
a seek ac I'm not an academic in seeks I
was brought up that way that doesn't
mean I know all the theory behind it so
I went around and I dug through all the
information and I realized those
explanations the research was solid but
the explanations weren't. So that's what
really triggered me. It's like, okay,
what makes this meditation work? It's
not to do with mudras. It's not to do
with hand positions. It's not to do with
imaging, but it is to do with slowing
down brain wave activity. when you
repeat
sama you know and you just repeat that
over and over again and it's a a nice
slow pace and you're breathing um more
easily more slowly and you slow down all
that activity when you bring in the
mudras which is touching the different
fingers for for the different words well
it's not the mudras necessarily that are
creating the effect it's a focus have
you ever tried trying to make make your
mind blank. It's impossible. As soon as
I sit down
to meditate, if I think, okay, I'm just
going to make my mind blank. No,
everything is going to flood through.
So, when you look at the elements in
this
meditation, that is what got my
attention more. Often times things are
simplified or mystified. you know, they
make it mystical and magical and it
doesn't need to be. So, that's really
what what triggered me was I came across
this. I didn't like the explanations.
Quite honestly, I found some of them
offensive. It's like don't don't distort
it. It's not even you there was an
explanation they gave where they said
that it was to do with um the pressure
points inside inside your mouth the the
tongue and where it hits in your mouth
but sat nama is not sat
nam it's not s it's s it's not t it's t
your mouth is totally different so when
you're looking at acupressure points
that's
ridiculous but the research was still
solid. And so as I started digging into
this and I started looking at all the
other things that we do, it was me
searching for what is it that really
works? Take out the mystical, the
magical, take out the the teachers, the
gurus that tell you to do things in
certain ways. I wanted to empower the
reader. I wanted to give them the
information. And so when I take this
particular meditation apart in the book,
I provide ways that you can personalize
it and make it your own. There is a
great value to faith. So whatever you
your background is, if you can
incorporate that, fine. If you don't
want to, that's fine. But I wanted to
make it work for you. I don't want to
create resistance in you to the actual
process. I want you to understand it,
personalize it and fly with it. And I
took that through, you know, all the
elements in the book, all the all the
research that is in the book. I try to
dig in deeper to find out what the truth
is. Yeah. Yeah. And you definitely you
laid a great scientific framework for
everything and you brought in a lot of
relatable stories. Um my attention was I
had no problems with my attention as I
was listening to your book. Um, so I I
converted over to audio and was
listening this morning as I was reading
along. Um, so how does it coincide with
your personal heal healing journey? So
how much of this was as as you're
learning? I mean some something I I
definitely want to learn about is uh you
healed your own rheumatoid arthritis.
Um, you stumbled upon a couple
supplements. I definitely want to hear
about all that. So, how did that lead
into as you're learning about yourself
and you're also learning about all this
other framework that you have, this
other background from you and your
husband's work? Um, how does it all
start leading in together? Life is a
journey. There isn't, you know, just
just one element to this. Yeah. The
whole thing has been me um not only
trying to become the best version of
myself. We were talking about that
earlier on. um but dealing with issues
that that I had as well. So there have
been several places where I have used
all these techniques. It actually
started from that. Um my degrees in
microbiology. I worked in a path lab.
One day there was a lecturer that w that
came around and this was advertised to
all the doctors and nurses and lab staff
at the hospital.
I had always thought hypnosis was
something people did on the stage. It
was rather silly. You do it for a laugh.
Didn't take it seriously at all. But
here was a presentation being funded by
the hospital. So it had a quasi
endorsement to it on hypnosis and
psychotherapy. So I attended this um I
knew for a fact during the actual
presentation that these weren't shills
because coincidentally it was a huge
auditorium. Coincidentally there were
about 70 people in my lab who attended
this seminar but they were distributed
throughout the lab and when he called up
subjects coincidentally he chose three
people from my lab. So I knew they
weren't shills. There were stories he
told. There was one particular story. I
repeat this one a lot cuz it just it
grabbed my attention. But there was a
woman who had a pain in her arm. She'd
had a pain in her arm for decades. She
had seen all the doctors, all the
specialists. They hadn't been able to
find anything. As a last resort, she
went for hypnosis. And under hypnosis,
they did the the regression. They go
back to the triggering event. And she
discovered there was an emotional event.
Something had upset her in the past that
she had packed away in a box. Didn't
think it was
significant, but that was the event that
she
remembered. The following day, she
called the hypnotherapist and said the
pain had gone. It had actually gone
immediately, but she didn't trust it.
So, she had waited to see and this pain
had gone. And I was fascinated by the
idea that the subconscious mind can have
such an effect on our
present from events that we've forgotten
about,
discarded. Um, it it it intrigued me. It
intrigued me. So, I went I had
hypnotherapy myself. I discovered some
fascinating techniques. I uh did
hypnotic drawing, hypnotic writing. With
the hypnotic drawing, they go back to
the traumatic event. And so the
hypnotherapist had me do this drawing
and I'm a really bad artist at the best
of times and at the end of the session I
looked down at my my piece of art and it
was just squiggles on a page and I
didn't have any idea what any of that
meant. Then the following week he
brought me back and told me to go back
to this and look at the picture and tell
him what it meant. Under hypnosis I knew
exactly. There was an event when I was
in school. I would have been eight,
nine, maybe 10. Um, we there was a
swimming pool at Esswall, just an above
ground pool and in the summer we would
go swimming. It wasn't proper swimming
lessons. It was just us kids splashing
around. But there was one day I was in
the pool and I have no idea why, but my
feet couldn't find purchase on the
ground. I could not get my feet under
me. My head was underwater. I'm
floundering away. It wasn't deep, you
know. Um, if I I could stand up easy.
Norm, I just could not stand up. A
teacher saw my difficulty, reached in,
pulled me up by my swimming cap.
Everything was fine. But I didn't tell
anybody how afraid I was. I didn't admit
it to myself that, you know, I came
close to drowning in a, you know, with a
whole group of people around me. But
under hypnosis, this trauma was unlocked
and it opened up parts of me. So that's,
you know, that was where my healing
journey started. I went on and did a
three-year course in hypnosis and
psychotherapy. Um, I then met my husband
and as said, he's an expert in the uh
preconscious processing field. So he's
got the patented inner talk subliminal
technology.
um I met him and I have been working in
the background with him doing the
research. So with the RA after my second
child was born I developed RA. I started
having random joint pains. It just got
worse and worse. By the time my son was
3 months old, I was having problems
changing his diaper because the pain in
my shoulder could be so bad. I couldn't
hold his legs up to put the diaper
underneath and that's really scary for a
new mom. So then I incorporated
everything I had learned. Um we have
this idea
that now I want I want everyone to be
cautious with how you take this
information. This is not about casting
blame of any kind. But if you try just
as an experiment to take full
responsibility for everything that goes
on in your life, it can open up avenues
of
opportunities. It can open up things
that you haven't thought to look at. So
I developed the
RA and I searched within myself. The
beauty of this is that you can do it.
You don't have to share the information.
You don't have to embarrass yourself by
telling everyone, you know, all of these
crazy things that you've done. And lots
of the ideas that come up may not be
correct anyway. But I went through this
the process and I thought, why am I
doing this to myself? What benefit do I
get from being sick? What is it that I
am trying to avoid? Why am I trying to
punish myself with this? So I did I did
all of that work. Some of the ideas were
nuts. Some of them maybe could be true.
I don't know. So I did all of that. I
also am fascinated by the placebo
response. Our minds have great healing
ability and there is so much research
there as well. So, I don't know about
how you turn on the placebo effect, but
I do know how to turn off those things
that can block us from healing
ourselves. So, if we believe that
everything is out there, things happen
to us, there's nothing we can do about
it. Um, sometimes you get sick and
that's all all there is to it. I didn't
want to go down that avenue. I wanted to
say my mind knows how to heal this. All
I have to do is believe it
enough. So I used we have an inner talk
subliminal program accelerated healing
and well-being. I played that program
every night all night for 15
months. So what I'm doing is just trying
to program as deeply as possible this
idea that my mind knows how to heal me.
I allow that to happen. Um I I can do
this. I take away the blocks that say I
can't do this and I replace it with I
can do
this. 15 months in, you know, I I looked
at alternative therapies. I didn't want
stuff that just helped. I wanted to cure
myself of this. I wanted it gone.
Absolutely. 15 months in, I came across
a supplement CMO. It's freely available
today on Amazon. It was just coming out
then. the developer of this, the
scientist behind it all, Dr. Sans was
alive still at the time and I contacted
his office to make sure there were no
contraindications with nursing my my
child at the same time. I took this
supplement, two tablets twice a day for
two
weeks and basically the RA went. Now, I
had tried to come off my RA meds before
that and it was not pretty. You know, I
could have these big flare ups. My
joints would, you know, ping and get
stuck in the wrong places. The pains
would would come back. I was unable
prior to this to come off the doctor
uh doctor prescribed
medications. But then I took the CMO for
two weeks. um came off my meds a week
after I had a pain in my shoulder. I
went back to the meds morning, night,
and morning. Following week, the pain
came back. I took the meds twice.
Following week, the pain came back. I
took the meds once. I've not taken any
RA meds for 25 years now. None at all.
No, no prescription meds either. Nope.
Nothing. Nothing at all. Wow. I don't
know, Jacob, what actually healed me.
Um, when it comes to healing ourselves
and personal development, sometimes you
don't have to know which element it was
that worked. I just know perhaps the CMO
if it was such a cure for RA, it would
be curing everybody and it's not. Yeah.
But it worked for me. Um, is it that my
particular RA responded well to that? Is
it that I had done all the other work
and I just needed this placebo response
to kick in? I needed to put it on
something else. Yeah. Yeah. All I know
is is that it worked. And so, yeah, this
was a significant issue to me. I will
try everything in my power to get it to
work. I think it was a combination. I
actually think it was a combination. I
programmed myself to to fully believe I
could heal myself. Um, I did the the
background work to say, is it this or is
it that that I'm gaining from from
getting sick? I did all of that work and
then I allowed the placebo to kick in. I
don't know, but it worked. I I do think
there is some sort of it's like an
accumulatory ripening of sorts. I'm in
I'm picturing a a bucket being filled
with water that has a you know a a
tipping point at the middle to when it
gets filled it finally tips over and all
the water dumps out. So once it gets to
the top it's now counterbalanced to tip
over. I think there's something about
that when it when it comes to our
healing. I talked to a couple people on
the podcast that they have found some
sort of supplement that seemed to have
kind of pushed them over and they could
mark that looking back as kind of when
it it really turned off or turned on
something and and it was a huge part of
their journey. It's very interesting.
There's something to that, right? There
is definitely a tipping point. That's
that's a great way to put it. You do all
of this work and then suddenly you can
have a breakthrough that seems magical,
but it's not. is the accumulated effect.
And that's something else that you see
in mind training. We look at the
accumulated effect like of optimism. Um
how that being optimistic today can have
farreaching ramifications to longevity,
health, prosperity,
relationships. But it does it it all
adds up. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Well, tell me
more about optimism. Tell me about the
the positive benefits of optimism. And
uh one of my notes that I wanted to
throw in there is can you feature
something for the people who have
trouble even like they just go I am just
a negative person. I'm just I just have
trouble with that. My first response is
always kind of negative. How do I bust
out of that? So uh give a give a gift to
those people as well please. There is so
much research on the benefits of
positivity and optimism. There are there
are research studies that show the
shortterm kinds of effects. So they have
people maybe they're writing in journals
and they're they're told to think of
something positive and they look at
these same people just 6 weeks
afterwards and they can find
alleviations from anxiety and stress to
long-term ones where they can look, you
know, 40, 50, 60 years down the highway
and show there was one research study
that I looked at. they were looking at
nuns. For some reason, they often look
at nuns, and I think it may be because
you've got this um controlled group of
people with the ability to go back and
look at the people again um long term.
But in this particular research study,
they the nuns were asked to keep
journals um and then they would analyze
the journals and mark them to degrees of
optimism and and positivity. And what
they found was those nuns who in their
20s had gone on uh who had just
expressed themselves more positively
when they were older, they would live
longer. They would live longer, they
would live happier. Um, one of the other
things that really fascinated me was
when they did autopsies afterwards as
well on these nuns, they could find nuns
whose brains were riddled with
Alzheimer's, but they never expressed
it.
They never expressed it at all. And I
found that really encouraging because
I'm in I'm in my 60s now. And so I
start, you know, those you could have
some of those fears. It's like I don't
fear dying. I don't fear lots of these
other things. But to lose myself in
dementia or Alzheimer's is is
significant. So it shows there the more
engaged you are with life, the more you
can put this stuff aside. And you know
with optimism they showed there's a
longitudinal nurses study that was done
and they showed that the more optimistic
nurses had significantly less chances of
dying from loads of diseases. So they
could have like a 16% lower chance of
dying from cancer or a 52% lower chance
of dying from
infection. That's absolutely huge when
it comes to cardiac health. Even if
you've got a history, a family history
of cardiac
disease, the optimistic people were a
third less likely to deal with cardiac
issues even with with that kind of of
strong history. So you say, how can you
how can you make yourself more optim
optimistic if you're
not? Very important question there
because some people are more
pessimistic. Some people are more
optimistic. Journaling is a really good
thing to do. That's something I would
suggest everyone do right now. And it
doesn't have to be detailed journaling.
I think at the end of the day, one of
the things I like to do, as I said, I
always combine all of these techniques.
I'm into saving time a lot. So, I will
combine techniques. So when I will when
I go to bed, I get into bed, I will do
some a bit of slow breathing. I do the
diaphragmatic breathing. We can talk
about that more in detail, but that is
just a process where it will
automatically help your brain produce
some of the happy brain chemicals. It
can uh relieve anxiety and stress. It's
it's a very mechanical process. So I can
be in bed. I will do maybe three. That's
all. It's not huge. I'm not going to
hyperventilate or anything, but I do a
few deep, slow breaths, allowing my
diaphragm to
expand. I'll do the forgiveness exercise
where I think about any anyone that may
have upset me and put out forgiveness.
There is great release that comes from
forgiving other people. and also for
forgiving myself. We make mistakes in
life. We we do things. We can say things
impulsively. It's important to forgive
ourselves and to allow others to forgive
us as well. But I do the forgiveness and
then I'll do the gratitude. I will stop.
And so I'm not actively journaling. I'm
not writing it down. Both processes are
good. Whatever works for you. But I will
stop and think of what am I grateful for
today? And sometimes it can be something
as simple simple as it was bright and
sunny today. I enjoyed seeing the
sunshine. I'm grateful for that. I'm
grateful for the ability to be able to
go out for a walk. I'm grateful for the
end of day chats I have with my husband
where we unwind, um maybe have a drink
together, crack a few jokes. I'm
grateful for these things. It can be I'm
grateful for my job. I'm grateful I can
uh provide for my family. I'm grateful
for the food that we've had today. It
doesn't have to be
huge. But gratitude
um taking some time to do that. And then
when you know you can take it even
further because some people will
ruminate on all the things that can
possibly go wrong. So now I'm outside of
my nighttime exercise. I'm talking about
just during the day. If you find
yourself ruminating on what could go
wrong, first of all, start paying
attention. Think about what you're
thinking about. Mindfulness, the real
mindfulness, not the fad mindfulness,
which everyone, you know, really is
meditation. I'm talking about really
think about what you're thinking about.
And if you find your mind going that
way, check yourself and say,
"Okay, I am sitting here thinking about
all the worst possible outcomes that
could happen. What would happen if I
thought about the best possible outcome?
What would that look like?" Start
painting that picture in your mind. What
would the best outcome, you know,
perhaps you're afraid of being fired and
instead you get a promotion. Imagine it.
create it in your mind. Paint that paint
that picture for yourself and then do
that to different degrees. What if that
worst possible outcome doesn't even
happen? Is it worth spending all of this
time worrying about something that may
not happen? If it does, I'll deal with
it then. But why waste my time right
now? Why not enjoy every moment that I
have right now? So the the pessimist
will notoriously ruminate on these bad
things. So for for that person I I would
say start asking yourself some different
questions. Start looking at it
differently. Start imagining a positive
outcome. Most of the time you will find
out that that worst possible thing
doesn't ever come to be. Yeah. Really
doesn't. You know, the vast majority of
the time the worst possible thing is not
going to happen. But you have to have
experience. You have to start seeing
that. So you have to start practicing it
right now. Test it out. Test it out for
yourself. Do your own scientific
experiment or non-scientific experiment
and test it out for yourself. Once you
start having those experiences, the
process gets easier and easier easier to
do. Yeah. Um and then you know if you
are very leftrain I would say read that
chapter in mind training. The evidence
is so deep on the the positive aspects
the positive
benefits you know the chances of getting
promoted are greater for optimistic
people. Better relationships better
prosperity just across the board better
health. Um and it feels good. Jacob.
Yeah. It simply simply feels good. So
why not do something that can that can
feel good? Yeah. Yeah. Precisely. Well
said. It's a I I get to these points
where cuz I'll be mean to myself and I'm
always working on having that gentle
relationship, you know. Um it's always
it's always a continuous flow. And uh
sometimes I'll get to the points where
it's just like, man, life is hard
enough. I don't need to be so mean to
myself. And it that could that alone
could be like, "Oh, yeah." And and I I
also love um you know, every time I
notice that I'm gentle with myself,
every time that I kind of relax a little
bit on me, it helps me remember that my
problems and my emotions and my feelings
aren't special to me. They're something
that all humans go through to some
degree, and it helps me just feel a
little bit more for other people as
well. So, it's a it's a reoccurring
cycle.
Um, okay. I I want to glance at my notes
and make sure I don't miss anything
super important.
Um, so how do
we what about what do you think about
the jump
from even learning that you the jump
from fixed mindset to growth mindset
basically? Because I think that can be
pretty profound for a lot of people. a
lot of people at the beginning of uh you
know a lot of later in life when we kind
of go oh I need to redirect and I need
to look at my childhood traumas I need
to look at how the things that happened
to me when I was younger reshaped me um
but to even get to that point you kind
of have to convince yourself or or hear
at least hear other people's examples of
um the fact that we could even change
that we're not just born a certain way
and everything not everything's
determined. So what do you think about
that that initial jump to even knowing
that you can develop a growth mindset?
That that's a complicated question,
Jacob. Um, one of the things that I have
found in this field is that there are
many many people who have the attitude
of I'm just the way I am. I'm the way
God made me, nature made me, genes made
me, circumstances made me. I can't
change anything.
So the very first step in change is
understanding that that you can change
and for some
people they're not there yet. So this
for me the spiritual aspect I find my
training is is very science-based. I
wanted to keep it 100% science-based but
I often find spirituality creeping out
in different places. So I read Robert
Sapolski's determined book and he does a
really thorough job at explaining why
free will does not
exist. Every every event has a precursor
to it. Maybe it's your genes, a prior
experience, something else there. So to
me the spiritual aspect of this I mean
he's absolutely correct. Free
will he says free will does not exist.
Period. And many many experts say the
same thing. That's not quite where I
land. I land on the fact that free will
isn't free. You have to take you have to
take the free will. There are places
where you where you can access that.
There is work that has been done. Um
Benjamin Libert in the 80s looked at uh
the the the brain and they look and they
find there's activity in the
subconscious mind before you make a
choice. So he did the first experiment.
There were several other experiments
done after that. Basically they're
asking people to choose whether they're
going to press a button with their right
hand or their left hand. Something
really
simple. and the the subject says when
they made the choice, but a technician
looking at, you know, um looking at the
equipment can predict up to 7 seconds
prior the choice that you're going to
make. So the subconscious mind holds all
of this information. It's making those
choices automatically. You know, you
look at Canaman's work, the thinking
fast and slow, the system one, system
two thinking. We think on automatic
pilot most of the
time but we can change that and access
more of the the system 2 kind of
thinking. So when you talk about free
will not being free you start saying
okay well I can take charge of how my
subconscious mind is programmed. So just
like the optimism and pessimism, the
pessimistic person automatically is
going to think the negative thoughts but
you take conscious control over that
over that and you start changing the
programming in your subconscious mind.
You look at how it gets programmed in
the first place. They often say that you
are um the best of the six people
closest to you. you'll be as successful
as those people. Or when it comes to
losing weight, your success will depend
on the people that you surround yourself
with. Or when it's relationships, if the
girls are together and they're all
complaining about their husbands, you're
going to find things to complain about
with your spouse. You know, you have to
look at all of these things. These
things are going into your subconscious
mind. But the beauty for me in the in
the free will argument isn't so much as
changing somebody else. Some pe people
have to get to that point where they see
the change. But you can be part of
somebody else's
experience. If you have discovered if
anyone listening to your podcast is
aware we have these abilities. They have
they already have the awareness that
there are things they can do. That's why
they're tuning in because they want to
learn more of these kinds of techniques.
They want to become the best version of
themselves. But as they change
themselves, they become part of somebody
else's experience. So you can have your
your circle of people and perhaps you
all thought first of all that you are
just the way that you are. You haven't
even thought about self-help. Self-help
gets a really bad rap. So there are lots
of fields
where it's not cool. It's not cool.
You're dumb to believe in this kind of
stuff. Um but when you start making the
change, then the people around you see
that change and they say, "Hey, maybe
there is something to this." And maybe
that's where you got the idea cuz you
saw what somebody else could do and you
say, "If they can do it, I can do it,
too." So actively changing the mindset
to come right back to the root of your
question. You know that that that is
challenging. Some things are going to
happen happen with time. I would say to
your entire audience, I say this, you
know, to everybody. Be the change that
you want to see in the world. You know,
the more you change yourself, the more
you improve yourself, the more the
happier you are, the happier you will
make everyone else. And they will get to
see that change is possible, too. Yeah.
Yeah. Well, well said. I think there's
definitely uh it's it's a beautiful art
to learn as you grow and experience
things
that not so much your natural state is
is so much who you are. It's kind of
like you can have these comfortable,
safe positions of you wake up and maybe
your first thoughts are are something
from the dream world, you're stressed
about something immediately, whatever
work, but you can choose to input more
thoughts. You could you could turn on
something that's positive. you you could
have an action um and it can you know
within 20 minutes you can kind of flip
the script of whatever your your mind
might have been telling you when you
first woke up and you discover that who
who you are is um it was strange timing
you discover that who you are
is the action the person who does the
action you know not so much the natural
state of immediately when you wake up
whatever your first thoughts are a lot
of times you discover that who you are
is the person who is on the other side
of doing something you know it's It's
the importance of action. So, um, on on
the importance of action, what more can
you tell me about the daily routine? Cuz
I feel like what it has to happen
is, you know, we insert these things and
we're like, it's 10 minutes on my
mindful minutes, you know, and then I
got five minutes on my journaling and
then I got breath work for, you know, I
think we start out a little precise or
at least me when I first started with a
lot of this, that's how I began and now
it's just a natural fluid part of my
movement in the morning. I wake up with
enough time to do these certain list of
things and it's not even a list anymore.
It's just a natural way of me landing
back. Um I had a friend to say uh
dethawing. Um it's it's a bit like that.
So what can you tell me about the art of
uh kind of making this a daily routine?
That's totally what mind training is
about. I'm not into um spending vast
amount of times doing I don't have time,
you know. I I I've raised a family. I've
got the business. I I've got a busy
lifestyle. So, what I want to do is
create things that can just become
habits. And as you said, first of all,
you start off doing things very
consciously. You're going to make an
effort to do some of these things. But I
want these things to start becoming
habit. So, they're just just normal. So,
you say in the morning, you open your
eyes first thing in the morning.
Sometimes we get out of bed the wrong
side. It's just it's just the way that
is.
And you can say, "I just got out of bed
the wrong side and that's going to
affect my whole day, blah blah blah."
Um, and you can just succumb to that. Or
you can say, "I got out of bed the wrong
side, but I can change this." And there
are things that you can do. There are
morning habits. Um, so just starting off
by saying thank you, you know, gratitude
for the day. Um, telling yourself you're
look thinking about what you're looking
forward to in that day. That could be a
great way. But there are really simple
things like smiling. You know, you get
out of bed the wrong side, you're
feeling grump grumpy. Um, but smiling
the very people often think that when
you're happy, you
smile. But it works the other way
around, too. When you smile, your brain
will produce the happy brain chemicals.
So, smiling will make you happy.
So, if you get out of bed and you're
grumpy, smile at yourself. Look in the
mirror. An exercise I like to do, I
don't only just do this in the morning.
I will do this throughout the day as
well, but I will add a little
mindfulness just into how I wash my
hands. So, it doesn't take any time.
You're washing your hands anyway, but
just spare a couple of seconds thought
to the feel of the water over your
hands, the lather, how soft it feels.
you know, you wash your hand, you can
have gratitude that the the water is
warm. Then look up in the mirror and
smile at yourself. I'm very much an
advocate of being kind to yourself. Be
nice to yourself. So, smile at yourself
and say, "You've got this, Rainda. You
can do this. It's okay." Um, make it
make it a great day. Talk to yourself.
Split seconds. That's all these things
take. Just just a few seconds. If you
can try and get sunlight first thing in
the morning. Again, that is going to
produce happy brain, happy brain
chemicals, the endorphin, the serotonin.
If you can step outside, feel the feel
the fresh air, you know, these things.
It can just be where I am, we've
actually got our office building and my
home, they are 2-minute walk from each
other. So, it's it's that twominute walk
from my home to my office and I can
breathe the air, breathe the fresh air.
If it's just rain, it have that special
smell. But I take the seconds to notice
that, to absorb that, to feel the awe,
to feel to hear the birds singing, to
feel the the breeze on my face. These
things don't take vast amounts of time.
If you're having a bad time during the
day, get up from your desk. Step
outside. If it's too cold, stand inside.
I will do that. Here in Spokan, the
winters can be so, so cold, but we can
still get lots of sunshine. So, I will
go stand by the window. I'm inside. It's
nice and warm, but I've got the sun
streaming on my face. And I'll do that
just for a few moments. You know, it's
it's all a two-way street. Nothing
nothing is difficult but in my training
at the end of each
chapter I go through because there is a
great deal of science there and I think
the science is important to convince you
that the work is necessary to do but I
will include a summary at the end of
each chapter to tell you why the
information was important but then I
give you
exercises exercises that you can do to
start incorporating and first of all
they are exercises the things that you
do, but after a while they become habit.
They they absolutely become habit. And
you're right, I don't think about most
of these things. Most of the time,
occasionally, if I'm having a a rough
day, I will deliberately go do something
to get myself out of it, but most of the
time I'm doing it automatically. Yeah.
Yeah. I think that's how it gets. I was
just thinking even how I normally do.
there was a period of time for every
podcast because I would get myself all
worked up about the importance of the
podcast and I got to make sure my mind
is the sharpest and all these things you
know and uh so I would have these just
structure I got to go to yoga class in
the morning and I got to make sure I do
this meditation or whatever and um now
it's just what whatever I need that day
right you know I just structure my day
for whatever feels the most intuitive
that day and uh about 5 minutes before I
sat down here to chat with you I was
kind of laying on my uh my foam roller
there just stretching out my posture and
I started going over my gratitude. Thank
you for this. Thank you for this. Ah,
what what a joy it is to be able to have
this opportunity. Wow. Like this
lighting looks really cool. I spent a
few minutes on it. I'm glad that I got
the right lighting. You know, just
simple things that uh help me. For me, I
call it landing back in my body. And it
just helps me pull in all these crazy
creative long expanded thoughts that um
are are fun and useful when they're
useful, but they're not always useful.
So, um, yeah, it it helps me just land
back in my body and it shows, Jacob. I
can see that on your face, you know. I
can see that that inner inner happiness,
inner contentment, the the empower.
Yeah. I used to be phobic about public
speaking. Absolutely phobic. When I
started doing these interviews, just
like you, I would do all the prep and
all the all of the other stuff. Um, with
time you just gain confidence in
yourself and I instead of focusing on
all all the science I want to remember
all the names and the dates and the, you
know, trying to sound impressive, I want
to keep it real. And so I I gain a lot
from these interviews because I'm
talking to to real people and we're on
this path together and and it feels
good. Yeah. It simply it simply feels
good to be in this circle of
people just just doing this. It it it's
real. It's real. It's it's not it's not
all theoretical. It's not about being
the most
successful, being the most prosperous.
It's about being the best version of
myself and actualizing myself. I want to
be myself. I don't want to be a carbon
copy of other people. I don't want to
comp compete with other people. Um that
that's not what life is about. I want to
fully blossom into into the into the
whole me. The whole me and what what is
me, not as I said what we are programmed
to think. And we are we are programmed.
There is stuff going on. Um there is
research going on around the world
trying to discover why we do what we do.
I'll ask you, Jacob. Who do you think
uses that information the most? The
media.
The media. Everybody in our magic
rectangle we call our phone. That's who
uses it. The
politicians. You know, we even heard
that President Obama had his dream team
of social psychologists. President Trump
had Cambridge Analytica. They're all
using this information. They're going to
try and tweak you. They're going to find
the words, the trigger points, all of
these things, all the ads that you see,
they're all trying to reach you on an
automatic level. So, learning some of
these processes, you don't need to know
all of
them. You just need to know that they
exist and they're going on. Just that
just that amount will give you pause for
thought. So, in my training, I do go
through the compliance principles,
things that they do to try and get you
to buy their product. One of the ads
that it just it's always got my
attention because you see the same theme
play over and over again where in the ad
someone hears about this amazing new
product that they've got to have and
they start to run to the store to get it
and then somebody else sees them running
so they have to run too. And soon
there's this whole sea of people
running, you know. Well, they they are
using compliance principles there.
They've got social proof. If everybody
else wants it, it has to be good.
They've got the scarcity. Look at all
these people going to get it. I better
go get mine right now. They're trying to
get you to move right now. And the fact
is, we don't always need to upgrade our
phones as soon as a new version comes
out. Our phones can work, you know,
really well. My last phone, I'd had it
for eight years before I changed it.
Eight, maybe longer than that, you know,
you don't need these things. But these
techniques are being used on you. Yeah.
Being used on you constantly. And having
an awareness of it gives you the ability
to to make your own choices. You're not
being driven by fears of of different
kinds. You can make a choice based on
what you want. Yeah. Yeah. It definitely
drives um I was hearing like a fear of
incompleteness. It definitely like
magnifies this feeling that we could all
be prone to. And it really tells you
like, well, I I'll feed that
incompleteness if you just come over
here, check out this bright, flashy
thing, come listen to this, come think
this way. Um and yeah, yeah, they can
use it against us. They can it it could
be a
very kind of a whole process really that
that may take a while when you kind of
first discover that oh you know the word
propaganda is is much more deep than I
thought and maybe some of my maybe I
should second guess a lot of the things
that I thought were for sure or that I
learned when I was growing up or from
certain textbooks whatever it is um it
it turn it turns you onto the path of
self-discovery for sure and that's
something I was thinking about with with
your book I feel like uh you use the
word self-actualiz or use actualization
at least Um, and I was thinking your
book certainly
is, you mentioned the psychocybernetics.
I remember reading that one as well.
That was a mind-blower. But, um, you're
kind of guiding people towards their own
path of self-actualization. Do do you
think about it intentionally that way or
um, yeah, you certainly are. Yeah, it's
great. The subtitle of the book is the
science of
self-empowerment. Um, maybe I've become
cynical to to a degree. I get tired of
people telling me the the right things
to do. There are lots of experts, okay?
So, you you go two ways. You get the the
the scientists doing all of their
research. Um, and there are some
fabulous books out there, but the books
rarely ever tell you how to put the
stuff into practice. There are lots of
self-help books out there, and they will
tell you what to do, but they don't tell
you why. And often times the information
is simply
incomplete. So and then they tell you
like manifesting you know for a period
that secret was really popular. Everyone
thought ask believe receive all I have
to do is do this. And I had literally I
talked to people constantly and I
remember having someone call me up and
they wanted a program to help them with
sales but they were a strong believer in
manifesting.
Um, and
so they wanted a program, but they
didn't want to play the program. I said,
"We have the inner talk subliminal
programs, but they didn't want to even
play it for an hour a day. They didn't
have that that much time. They wanted a
program that they could just play, and
they wanted it to magnetically bring
sales to them. They didn't want to do
anything to promote sales. They didn't
want to go find new customers. They I
promise you they wanted to sit there
manifest and have the phone just ring.
Well, that's how it works, right?
No, but there but but it got it got
hyped up so much. There are people that
believe that and that stuff is
dangerous. You know, there is something
to be said for what you expect you get
because that's what you pay attention
to. That's where your attention goes to
when you start expecting these things.
That's what you see. Like if you're
going to buy a new car and you've done
your research and you've chosen the
make, the model, whatever, then all of a
sudden that's the car that you see. So
there are elements, you know, there are
kernels of truth in this.
Um, but I very much believe in putting
action behind everything. I want. So
often when it comes with manifesting,
you get people that teach the law of
attraction. There's no such thing as a
law of attraction. Um just kernels in
there that are worth holding on to. Um
but then when it doesn't work, they will
tell you that you weren't doing it
enough. You weren't believing enough or
you were holding on to it. You've got to
believe it and then release it cuz as
long as you're holding on to it, you
haven't believed it yet. They're telling
you how you are deficient. And that
stuff annoyed me. It absolutely annoyed
me. And that was why I wanted to throw
away all the fluff, all of this kind of
stuff. I didn't want a self-help book
that says that if it's not working for
you, you're not doing it right. I wanted
to give you the information to find out
for yourself why it's not working for
you. I wanted this to be very much a
personal process of self-empowerment.
Empower yourself. I want to give you all
the tools. Now go away and make it your
own. Make it your own. Take the elements
that work for you. You don't have to do
everything. But the fact is you start
doing some things, some things work, and
then maybe you add something else into
your mix, and then you add something
else in. You find out what is
comfortable for you. But being true to
yourself is what this life's journey is
all about. Yeah. Yeah. In in in the
healing journey, the self-empowerment
journey is certainly one that leads you
back to yourself um in in a in a in a
way that you you learn about yourself in
a way that you didn't think you were
going towards. It's a it's a wonderful
path. So, I want to me you mentioned at
some point in your book um kind of
briefly, but it sparked a curiosity. You
mentioned a right of patch uh passage.
our our um society doesn't really have a
right of passage. And I've read this
book uh Brian Marescu. It's the secret
history of the religion with no name.
It's about the eiscinian mysteries and
they used to take this urgot and they
used to um drink this psychedelic drug
and it was basically a I think a male
thing but a ride of passage for for
cultures. Um and I I wonder what you
think about that in our modern age. Do
you think that there is some sort of
like is there pseudo rights of passage
that are taking place that we're
desiring? Should we bring back a right
of passage? Um I guess what do you think
about the modern world and rights of
passage?
You know, you're right. There aren't
rights of passage in the same way. I
don't know. That's not something I've
given a great deal of thought to. Fact
is, we are brought up, you know, our
parents, um, teachers, whatever. As
children, we're always told what to do,
the right thing to do. We're told that
we're children, that we we, you know, we
have to pay
attention, pay attention to the
adults. And we don't normally have um a
way through that. For me, I suppose a
ride of passage was when I went away to
university. that I think is for me it
was one of the easiest ways to to grow
up. I'm fortunate I went to university
University University of Aberestworth in
Wales. Um it's a very isolated kind of
place but whenever they're doing polls
it has the it's always there either
number one or number two for student
satisfaction. So my college experience
was very different say to my boys
college experience. They went to the
University of Washington which is huge
and it's very impersonal and there's a
whole bunch of stress. Me my college
experience was amazing and I was in an
environment that was very accepting and
then I was with people my own age. So we
learned to do things for for ourselves
and it was okay to make mistakes. So
university or going away to college can
be a right of right of passage.
Um but that that can be a difficult
thing that goes on. There used to
be I don't know that it is so much the
case now, but there is this mentality
that when you're 18, you're an adult, so
you go out and it's like you have this
hard line without any of the the respect
that that goes with that. Um, when we
talk about the rights of passage for
certain cultures, there can often be
something that is done like a ceremony,
a bar mitzvah, you know, in the in the
Jewish faith, there can be, you know,
some process that the
child feels accepted into the adult
world. So, I I think that those things
could be could be really helpful. Um,
when you've got a good support
structure, you know, you've got the
older generation, uncles, friends,
family, those things could be really
helpful. Um, but they don't really exist
now. So, yeah, if you have the ability,
if you've got that that kind of
structure, doing something for your your
teen as they are becoming young adults.
Um, yeah. would would be would be
helpful. It would give them greater
respect, greater selfrespect, greater
faith in their in their own abilities so
they don't go from a child who has to do
what they're told to all of a sudden
they're just thrown out in the cold.
Having something where where the older
generation says, "You're here now.
You're here now. You're smart. You've
grown up. You've learned everything that
I can teach you. Now it's for you to go
out and teach yourself, learn from life,
learn learn what is good, but take the
values that we have imparted on you.
That would be great. Yeah. Yeah. I think
it's a Yeah. It's the less of the art of
throwing them over overboard of the ship
and telling them to swim and and more of
like giving them some some minimal
supplies in a raft and and sending them
in the direction that they want to go in
that they're already like whatever
they're interested in. You know, give
give them a push in whatever support
that you can and um you know wish them
the best. I was just thinking how how
sweet it would have been how on fire I
would have been if when I turned you
know 17 18 if I had gone to one of these
big Tony Robbins events that they have
nowadays. I mean, that would have been
crazy. I would I'm sure I would have
been fired up. Probably just way too
overly confident in in an insane way,
but that would have been quite the
adventure. Um Um Okay. So, so now that
you've written your book, now that you
you've compiled it,
um where do you see where do you see the
next 10 to 15 years to 20 years of not
just your work and and what you're going
to focus on, but kind of the whole world
of of self-development, psychology? Um,
do you think, you know, cuz some of
these things are pretty profound. If we
could start narrowing in and and both
narrowing in and expanding on the fact
that our thoughts can can give us our
sickness, quote unquote, or or, you
know, the the process of solving and and
the process of self-development could
cure us, quote unquote. Um, where do you
see the future of all this?
I think for myself going forward, life
is about exploring who I am and what I
understand. So my interests go, you
know, beyond science. They they they go
to the spiritual realms, too. I'm
constantly um searching that for what
feels real. I don't like easy answers in
any area.
Um, so for me, I I I want to continue
exploring that, exploring what I what I
think I know. Um, not just what sounds
good, what feels good. Um, when it comes
to the whole field of
self-help, you know, the fact is, Jacob,
lots of these ideas get recycled.
There's a great deal of stuff. Even the
law of attraction isn't, you know, it
didn't come out in the 2000s. That's
based on earlier work and that's based
on earlier work. There are ideas that
get re that get recycled and I think the
the languaging just just changes. So I
suppose I'm not out to make drastic
changes in the world. All I want to do
is be a positive influence on those
people around me and those people that I
can interact with. Those people who want
to hear it will hear it and it will
improve their lives and my spiritual
process. This idea of free will be the
example. Go out there. I think you know
what one of the things I do find
interesting is the self-help industry
was much more of an industry
uh 10 20 years ago. I think you had some
of the bigger names and maybe it's a bit
like religion when people start to
realize, hang on, there's flaws in this.
This isn't this isn't quite correct. And
so you have it with self-help. It
becomes this huge big craze and then
people start seeing flaws in it and it's
like no, it's not all about rah rah rah,
be happy, be positive that you know,
you've got to you've got to keep it
real.
So maybe I again it's not something that
I'd really thought about Jacob. So
thanks for bringing up the question but
I do think there'll be another
development. I think people are thinking
more and more today. There is a hunger
out there to improve ourselves, but
people want it realistic. At the younger
people, the Gen Z, the millennials, they
don't want to be fobbed off with a god
in the sky with a white beard who's
going to just give them everything. They
don't want the secret, this cornucopia
of everything is going to be hunky dory.
They they want real things that they're
very discerning.
And it's a little bit sad right now
because there is a great deal of anxiety
and depression in those
generations. But I I think as I'm
talking to you, I think a great deal of
positive will come out of that because
they're not accepting the status quo.
They're questioning. You don't have to
do things the same way. And that's how
how the world the world develops. you
start
questioning what are the norms and so
and so that's a good thing. So yeah, I
think in the long run as I said I'm
thinking out loud with you Jacob but my
answer is changing as I'm speaking to
you but I I think it'll become more and
more realistic and more and more
empowering.
Yeah, I do I do it. It'll be real. It
won't be the the rah rah stuff that that
becomes silly, you know, five easy ways
to explain to karma like no, it doesn't
work that way. 10 steps to
enlightenment. Yeah, there you go. Like
that's not it. But but there is a
journey and life itself is a journey and
when you can enjoy all of it and when
you can discover your own places of
power within that when you take back
control over yourself then it then it's
a wonderful journey and you just keep on
growing and it's fabulous.
Brilliant. Yeah. Well well said. I I
think it's all such a journey back
to I can never seem to decouple things
from identity. Identity becomes, you
know, when you get on to
self-development is just who who am I?
Who do I want to be? Um how do my
actions every single day equate to how I
see myself? You did a nice job of
splitting those into into different you
explored like the super ego and the ego
in the book. Um
um yeah, it's all fascinating stuff. I I
think everyone, you know, the younger
generation, I work a lot of these um I
work live event production. So just
sometimes I'm DJ, sometimes director,
sometimes I'm just all around um live
events. A lot of my work is in these
nonprofit um high school leadership
conferences. And um man, some of these
kids impress me. They they really
they're so sharp. They uh they're
individuals. They um they have they're
just they're learning all the time. you
know, you just watch and just their
brains are just firing. They're
learning. They're they're intuitive.
They're so confident, you know. Um, so
I'm excited for the future. I'm excited
for, you know, their journey of um, you
know, it seems like the millennial
crowd, we went through this whole like
childhood trauma and we're going to heal
our childhood trauma and and remap what
what our parents did. That kind of
seemed like it was my my generation's
thing. But, um, I'm looking forward to
what the journey looks like for the for
the younger generation as well. You
know, it's it's exciting.
Yeah, it is indeed. It is indeed. I I I
think it I think it's amazing. And yeah,
when you talk about millennials and
going back and healing healing trauma,
you know, there's a time and a place
there are some things that you need to
go back and and look at. And that's
where hypnotherapy, psychotherapy can be
be really beneficial. Um there are
things in mind training where I do
highlight the different things you're
supposed to learn at different ages and
how you progress successfully through
everything. So that gives you a
framework of where to look. Sometimes
you don't have to have somebody else. Um
you don't have to talk about these
things to other people, but you can look
at your own life and say, "Oh, that's
where my inadequacies and insecurities
come from. I see it." when it when you
bring it out into the light of day, it
can often lose its power. So, there are
places that it's worth looking back. And
there are other places it's like just
forge forward. Just go forward and
um m make things better going forward.
You don't have to be you don't have to
be controlled by your past. Yeah. You
know, so so there's a time and a place
for both approaches. Yeah. And I think
something that I found for myself that I
tried to like make known um when I when
I look back and I'm you know kind of
giving advice or or giving someone else
my input um is you don't have to you
know clean the entire bottom of the
ocean when you're healing your stuff
when you're when you're working on your
stuff when you're trying to improve
certain things. For me, I had a while
where I was just like I just took a
shovel to everything and I'm like it
happened in my childhood. I'm going to
dig it up and like you know some people
get caught up in trying to solve like
the whole lineage that you know all of
my ancestors I'm going to heal all of
your trauma and you know whatever your
path is but um you know be easy on
yourself too I think is is a very
important important rule of thumb here.
You know I'm I'm sure you'd probably
agree on that. Definitely. I'm a strong
believer in self-care. Um, I'm a strong
believer in creating happiness now. Um,
doing what what we can right now to you
take it one step at a time. Some people
have these, you know, huge goals. I've
literally had people come in with this
huge long laundry list of all the things
that they want to do. And I always say,
it's too big. That's too much. You can't
fix everything all at once. But what you
find is that if you look at today, what
would make me happier today? What would
help me feel better about myself
today? You just take it one day at a
time. And then you will frequently find
that when you deal with it that way,
some of the other problems just fix
themselves. They they do. I would tell
you that just my own life experience
that you can have this big long list but
you start doing one or two of them and
you'll find the others resolve
themselves. So yeah, maybe you want to
look backwards sometimes. Maybe you just
want to say no what what would help me
feel better? What would help me feel
better right now? How can I reduce my
anxiety today?
Step outside and feel the sun on your
face. Um and tell yourself that you have
the power You know, that's has to be one
of the most important things. It's not
that I'm unhappy today, so the world is
doing it doing it to me or my chemistry
is doing it to me. I can change that. I
can change it. It may not change
everything. I may not, you know, go from
depressed to being euphoric in one go,
but I can move that scale. I have more
control. And the more I do, the more it
will work and the better tomorrow will
be. Yeah. Yeah. Absolutely. It's really
about not always trying to solve the
answer or you know see how the daunting
staircase can be so intimidating to you
but you can take a step or two today and
and that is enough and tomorrow however
you're feeling you reapproach how much
can I get done today cool get it done
and then be easy on yourself at the end
of the day with how much you did get
done it's it's a journey it's it's a
whole process um okay so we are getting
up here in time I um you have given us
so many wonderful um
There there's been so much so many
things that people can try, activities,
actions that they can take. We already
have so many. Um but if I could ask you
if you could think of one more that
maybe wasn't mentioned or the the
juiciest fruit um just something that so
people are listening right now, whatever
day it is, tomorrow they're going to
start doing this thing. They're going to
do some percentage of this thing.
Anything come to mind that we didn't
mention? You know, my biggest thing is
one that most people don't take
seriously at first and that is
smiling. Smiling. You don't realize
first stop start start paying attention.
You know, there are lots of younger kids
today who lots of people in general
don't smile, but younger kids in
general, you know, they don't smile in
greeting. You get that head nod. That
funky head nod. Yeah. What's that?
So, start paying attention to smiling.
You'll discover people don't smile as
much as as you think. But when you smile
at someone, you make them feel cared
for. You make them feel welcome. You um
make them trust you more just smiling.
But smiling for yourself brings on your
own happy brain chemicals. It makes you
feel better. It reduces your stress
levels um long-term results. You know,
as I said, you can increase relationship
success, whatever. But just for today,
so I would say that has to be the first
thing. Pay attention to how much you
smile. Ask your partner, ask your
friends around you how much you smile.
And then go out of your way to be nice
to people. And that doesn't mean, you
know, give them all the cash in your
wallet, anything like that. Smile at
them. People want to be appreciated.
They want to be liked. Everyone has
their
insecurities. All of these fears, we all
have this. Um, if you get outside of
yourself and realize that if you're
feeling insecure, other people are
feeling insecure. And if you can make
them feel more secure, then that is all
part of a of a two-way street. And that
again comes down to the beauty of life,
the journey itself. So yeah, it sounds
really small. I would recommend everyone
read mind training to understand why
smiling is so important. Um I we cannot
do it justice in an interview like this.
There is so much there. But yeah, that
that's that's a a huge key. smile. Yeah,
I I love that one. I uh I try to as much
as I I'm actually a pretty natural
introvert, but I go on walks this path
by my house is so wonderful. But uh it's
one of my favorite things to try to do
is is look up, get out of my own head,
whatever headphones I'm listening to,
smile at people. A lot of times it's
like, "Oh, I feel better. I think they
probably feel better." It's it's great.
I smile at the dogs, too. That's always
just a positive for everyone. It is.
There's another really good one there is
is to do with hugs. and they were
talking about um the oxytocin that gets
released when you give someone a hug.
When that person wants to be hugged, but
a beautiful part of it is it works for
your dogs, too. So, you know, if you're
feeling down, go hug your dog. Go hug
your dog. You're gonna you're going to
feel better. Um yeah, if you're passing
people on the street, smile at them. It
feels good when people smile back. And
if you smile, smiling's infectious. Be
part of the change. Enjoy it all. Yeah,
it absolutely is. And you know, they
always say if you can get out of your
own head and think of someone else. If
you can serve someone else, you can stop
thinking about yourself and then you're
not depressed anymore. If you're
depressed, you're thinking about
yourself. You can almost guarantee it.
So, um, yeah, that's also wonderful.
Thank you so much for your time. Thank
you for this. Um, make sure we send
everybody I'll have the links below and
all that, but send everybody to your
book. Where do we find more on you? Um,
tell me about your social media, all of
that.
You can find the book Mind Training the
Science of Self-Empowerment wherever
books are sold, Amazon, Barnes & Noble,
whatever country you're in. The the big
bookstores are are going to have it. And
if they don't have it in stock, they
they can order it in. You can visit my
website, which is simply
raindataylor.com. So that's R A V for
Victor, I N D for dog,
erinder, rainda.com.
If you read my training, if you've just
had value from this interview and you
have some feedback, I would love to hear
from you. And you can email me directly
at rainda
ravindaaylor.com. Um, social networking,
I'm on Facebook and Instagram. I'm doing
a bit more LinkedIn. I'm doing more. I'm
getting there. But Facebook and
Instagram are going to be my primary
places. And I would I would love to
interact with you. It's a journey. it
it's fun. Let's do this together and um
enjoy it all. Yeah. Brilliant. Well,
yeah. Hopefully hopefully some of the
listeners uh um check you out. I think
they'll enjoy it very much. You got my
five star review. I've I've got a little
bit more left of the book, but I've read
a good good portion of it and I'm
enjoying it. I can't wait to finish. So,
you got my my sign off on that for sure.
Um Jacob. Yeah. Well, well, thanks again
so much for your time. Um listeners, you
know the drill. What do I say every
time? Have you stretched today? Move
your body a little bit. Drink a little
bit of water. If you drank no water
today, what are you doing, man? Drink
some water. Stretch. Love yourself. And
uh check out the guest book. You're
going to love it. All right, I'm going
to stop this recording
here. Wonderful. Well, hey, thanks. That
was great.
[Music]
Knowledge is power.
Reality
[Music]
is Junkyard Love podcast.